Finding Aid for American Society for Information Science and Technology Records, 1925-2001
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
American Society for Information Science and Technology Records1925-2001 1937-2000
American Society for Information Science and Technology
185 linear feet in 188 boxes
Photographs are primarily in boxes 149-156.
Audio material is primarily in boxes 172-187.
Visual material is primarily in boxes 121, 169, 173-187.
Most printed materials have been removed and cataloged separately. Newsletters are scattered throughout the collection.
ASIS&T
ASIS&T (or ASIST) is a professional association which creates, organizes, disseminates, and applies knowledge regarding information and its transfer. ASIS&T was preceded by the American Documentation Institute (ADI), which was founded in 1937 with the goal of acquiring and indexing the knowledge of the world. Name changes followed in 1968 (ASIS) and 2000 (ASIS&T). The records consist of correspondence, business and financial documents, minutes, bylaws, memoranda, manuscript and printed journal articles, printed promotional material, microfiche, photographs, and audio and video tapes covering the society's activities (and those of its predecessor organizations) from 1925 to 2001, with the bulk falling between the 1930s through 2000. Organizational business affairs and activities, including the conceptual evolution of its purpose and mission, are well-documented in several series, most notably in the Council Files. These broad areas are also covered in the Committee Files, but in a more detailed fashion, focusing on specific activities or issues. This series also represents the scope of ASIS's liaison committees, ranging from the American Library Association to the Egyptian Society for Information Technology. Documents generated by ASIS-approved regional and student chapters and the organized professional groups within ASIS devoted to special interests (SIGs) are found in the large Chapter Files and Special Interest Groups series. The Publications series includes significant editorial and administrative documents as well as some manuscript submissions for the "Annual review of information science and technology, and the Bulletin of the American Society for Information Science." Special note may be made of the Special Libraries Association Merger Files which chronicle the history of the ultimately unsuccessful merger of ASIS and SLA. The main correspondents found in the collection include: Robert McAfee, Assistant Executive Director; Joshua I. Smith, Executive director (1973-1976); Bonnie Carroll, Councilor and President; Linda Resnik, Executive Director (1985-1988); Samuel Beatty, Executive Director (1976-1984); and John Brokenshire, ASIS Financial Officer.
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center) Power Collection for the Study of Scholarly Communication and Information Transfer
1988-; additions are anticipated.
The record group is open for research, with some exceptions. See Restricted Material section below for details.
Access has been restricted to some documents in the ASIS records due to privacy and legal concerns. The restrictions are as follows:
Restricted Material
Boxes 6-19: The Council Meeting Minutes are closed for a period of 30 years from the date of creation of the records unless prior permission in writing is obtained from ASIS.
Boxes 130-145: The entire Financial series is closed for a period of 30 years from the date of creation of the records unless prior permission in writing is obtained from ASIS.
Box 188: Certain tax documents have been closed for a period of 75 years from the date of creation of the records (access open 2035-2068).
The holdings of the Special Collections Library include several other collections that researchers interested in ADI/ASIS/ASIS&T should consult. Vernon Tate's collection contains material on ASIS’s early history. He attended the organizing meeting in March 1937 and was president of ADI from 1948 to 1949. Tate also served as the editor of both the Journal of Documentary Reproduction and American Documentation. The Special Collections Library also holds the Cloyd Dake Gull Papers. Gull was president of ADI in 1960. Other related collections at the library include the National Microfilm Association Records, among other collections that form part of the Power Collection for the Study of Scholarly Communication and Information Transfer.
Most printed materials have been removed and cataloged separately.
The American Society for Information Science, as it has been known for the greater part of its history, is non-profit professional association that creates, organizes, disseminates and applies knowledge regarding information and its transfer. The mission of ASIS (now known as ASIS&T or ASIST, the American Society for Information Science and Technology) is "to advance the information sciences and related applications of information technology by providing focus, opportunity, and support to information professionals and organizations." (ASIS&T web site, http://www.asist.org)
ASIS’s predecessor was founded in 1937 by Watson Davis as the American Documentation Institute (ADI). Davis and 35 other documentalists met on March 13 to create an organization devoted to the idea of acquiring and indexing the knowledge of the world.
ADI was a service organization whose members were nominated by and affiliated with scientific and profession societies, foundations and governmental agencies. Initially, its primary interest was in microfilm as an aid to learning and the dissemination of learning. Involved in developing microfilm readers, cameras and services, ADI fostered negotiations and research which resulted in the "gentlemen's agreement" covering the duplication of copyrighted materials, the establishment of programs for the storage and reproduction of auxiliary materials in support of journal editors, and the support of international science communications.
The Journal of Documentary Reproduction, edited by Vernon Tate, was published from 1938 to 1942 to serve as an impartial source for the scientific aids to learning for the members of ADI. In 1950 ADI revived their publishing program with American Documentation, edited by Vernon Tate. This publication was to serve as a clearinghouse for information about documentation.
The Presidents of ADI/ASIS were leaders in the field of documentation and information science:
Presidents of ADI/ASIS
1938-1943; 1946 Watson Davis
1944 Keyes Metcalf
1945; 1947 Waldo G. Leland
1948-1949 Vernon D. Tate
1950-1952 Luther H. Evans
1953 E. Eugene Miller
1954 Milton O. Lee
1955 Scott Adams
1956 Joseph Hilsenrath
1957 James W. Perry
1958 Herman H. Henkle
1959 Karl F. Heumann
1960 C. Dake Gull
1961 Gerald J. Sophar
1962 Claire K. Schultz
1963 Robert M. Hayes
1964 Hans Peter Luhn
1965 Lawrence B. Heilprin
1966 Harold Borko
1967 Bernard M. Fry
1968 Robert S. Taylor
1969 Joseph Becker
1970 Charles P. Bourne
1971 Pauline A. Atherton
1972 Robert J. Kyle
1973 John Sherrod
1974 Herbert S. White
1975 Dale B. Baker
1976 Melvin S. Day
1977 Margaret T. Fischer
1978 Audrey N. Grosch
1979 James M. Cretsos
1980 Herbert B. Landau
1981 Ruth L. Tighe
1982 Charles H. Davis
1984 Don King
1985 Bonnie C. Carroll
1986 Julie A. C. Virgo
1987 Thomas H. Hogan
1988 Martha Williams
1989 Toni Carbo Bearman
1990 Tefko Saracevic
(See ASIS web site at http://www.asist.org for listings of more recent presidents and other officers.)
In 1950 the Library of Congress became the home of ADI, and remained so for the next ten years. The President's Newsletter was created to facilitate communication between the members. As the number of individuals involved in documentation and information services and the resultant new principles and techniques increased, ADI, in 1952, amended its Bylaws to admit individuals as well as corporate members. Thus, ADI became a national professional society concerned with all elements and problems of information science.
The 1950s saw an increasing awareness of the potential of automatic devices for literature searching and information storage and retrieval. During the 1960s problems created by the information explosion became a national concern.
In the 1960s ADI adopted an executive director system of management. These individuals served ADI/ASIS in this capacity:
Execuitve Directors of ADI/ASIS
1960-1963 John B. Kaiser
1963 Paul C. Janaske
1964-1969 James E. Bryan
1970-1973 Herbert R. Koller
1973-1976 Joshua I. Smith
1976-1984 Samuel B. Beatty
1985-1988 Linda Resnik
1988- Richard Hill
To reflect the changes in its range of activities and the emergence of information science as an identifiable discipline, the membership changed ADI to the American Society for Information Science (ASIS). This change came into effect on January 1, 1968. ASIS emphasized that its membership was uniquely concerned with all aspects of the information transfer process.
In December 1968, the presidents of ASIS and the Special Libraries Association met to explore the possibility of merger, because of similar interests and membership. The following year, the SLA Board and the ASIS Council approved the investigation of merger possibilities, by appointing a committee to discuss the benefits and feasibility of such a venture. An "Implementation Plan" written in December 1969 was rejected by the ASIS Council. The SLA Board accepted the Plan in principle, subject to further negotiations. In April 1970, three major snags--Scope and Name, Headquarters Location, and Project Work--remained to be solved. Negotiations continued, but by August 1971 the issue was dead.
The decade of the 1970s saw continued rapid growth in ASIS. The period was not without its problems, however. The publications program was expanded. The Bicentennial Meeting on Information was very expensive to put on and not particularly well attended. This precipitated a financial crisis that forced ASIS to cut back on some of its programs. With financial assistance from its membership and related organizations, ASIS was able to weather this crisis.
Further changes occurred in the 1980s, with ASIS adding emphases on personal and office computer systems and rural and community information services and intensifying its focus on international information issues. Through the 1990s and into the 21st century, ASIS has continued to examine diverse aspects of information science, including theory, technical issues, and social ramifications, with special focuses on database development and the World Wide Web.
In 2000, ASIS underwent another name change, becoming ASIS&T (also known as ASIST), the American Society for Information Science and Technology, in an effort to better reflect the concerns and pursuits of its membership.
The ASIS records cover the period from 1925 through 2001. The bulk of the documentation covers the years 1937 through 2000. The records of the American Society of Information Science are arranged into sixteen series, as shown in the following table (series are shown in alphabetical order, rather than by their physical arrangement).
Summary Contents List
Administrative -- Boxes 20-24
Annual Meetings -- Boxes 149-156
Awards -- Boxes 97-112
Chapters -- Boxes 36-57
Committees -- Boxes 71-96
Convention Audio/Video Tapes -- Boxes 173-187
Correspondence -- Boxes 25-35
Council -- Boxes 5-19
Financial -- Boxes 130-145
Grants and Contracts -- Boxes 146-148
Irene Farkas-Conn Historical and Research Files -- Boxes 1-4
Membership -- Boxes 113-114
Publications -- Boxes 115-129
Related Organizations and Subjects -- Boxes 157-171
Special Interest Groups -- Boxes 58-70
Special Libraries Association Merger -- Box 172
For the purpose of clarity, the organization shall for the most part be referred to as "ASIS"--the name by which it has been known for most of its history and to which it is mainly referred in the records--throughout this section.
Throughout the record group, the year listed for a folder is often the fiscal year rather than calendar year. This is particularly so for records in the Financial series. The fiscal year for ASIS runs from October through September.
Subjects:
American Society for Information Science. Bulletin of the American Society for InformationScience, 1971-1981.; American Society for Information Science. Journal of the American Society for Information Science, 1970-1980.; Special Libraries Association.; persname; geogname; Information science -- Congresses.; Information science -- History -- 20th century.; Information science -- United States -- Societies,etc.; Information storage and retrieval systems --Research.; Information storage and retrieval systems --Standards.; Professional associations -- United States.
Contributors:
American Documentation Institute.; American Society for Information Science.; Special Libraries Association.; Aines, Andrew A.; Airhart, Truett.; Armstrong, Anne A.; Bearman, Toni Carbo.; Beatty, Samuel B.; Bellardo, Trudi.; Berger, Mary.; Borko, Harold.; Brokenshire, John B.; Broome, F.K.; Bryan, James Edmund, 1909-; Carroll, B. (Bonnie); Caudra, Carlos A.; Cochrane, Pauline A. (Pauline Atherton),1929-; Creps, John E.; Crestos, James M.; Davis, Charles Hargis, 1938-; Day, Melvin S.; Debons, A.; Farkas-Conn, Irene Sekely, 1928-; Fischer, Margaret F.; Fry, Bernard Mitchell, 1915-; Garfield, Eugene.; Grosch, Audrey N., 1934-; Heilprin, Laurence B., 1906-; Herrman, Roy.; Heumann, Carl.; Holmes, Edith.; Kilgour, Frederick G.; King, Donald Ward, 1932-; Kochen, Manfred.; Koller, Herbert B.; Krcmar, Jan.; Landau, Herbert B.; Lunin, Lois F.; Marron, Harvey.; McAfee, Robert.; Mooers, Calvin N., 1919-; O'Dette, Ralph E.; Orne, Jerrold, 1911-; Plateau, Gerald O.; Resnik, Linda.; Rush, James E.; Salton, Gerard.; Saracevic, Tefko.; Sawyer, Edmond J.; Shera, Jesse Hauk, 1903-; Slater, Frank, 1928-; Smith, Joshua I.; Sophar, Gerald J.; Spaulding, Frank H.; Swanson, Rowena W.; Tighe, Ruth L.; Virgo, Julie A., 1944-; White, Herbert S.; Williams, Martha E.; Wooster, Harold.
Genre Terms:
Audio tapes.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Memorandums.; Microfiche.; Minutes.; Photographs.; Reports.; Videotapes.
- IRENE FARKAS-CONN HISTORICAL AND RESEARCH FILES
  The IRENE FARKAS-CONN HISTORICAL AND RESEARCH FILES series (3.5 linear feet) is made up of research materials compiled by Irene Farkas-Conn for her book on the history of ASIS, From Documentation to Information Science: The Beginnings and Early Development of the American Documentation Institute-American Society for Information Science (New York: Greenwood Press, 1990). Farkas-Conn was a past officer of ASIS and an information and management consultant. The series consists of original ASIS documents, various photocopies, and Dr. Farkas-Conn's notes.
  In the course of her research, Farkas-Conn acquired a substantial amount of very early, original ADI/ASIS records, spanning the 1930s through the 1960s. She also received small batches of related materials from individuals involved in ASIS (past leaders including Watson Davis, Vernon Tate, Cloyd Dake Gull, and Karl Heumann). Those records considered to be the most vital (such as articles of incorporation, early Council minutes, correspondence of ASIS founders and officers, etc.), and for which no other copy exists, have been put back into something approximating their original context. In some cases, however, original documents have been left within the Farkas-Conn research files, especially when they have been annotated by Dr. Farkas-Conn and grouped by her according to a particular subject.
  A small amount of materials was photocopied from the archives of other institutions, including the Smithsonian Institution Archives, the Bentley Historical Library at the University of Michigan, the Library of Congress, and Harvard University Archives. Permission to quote from or reproduce these documents must be obtained from these repositories.
  Some of the material in this series pertains to Science Service and its daughter agency Bibliofilm Service, both of which were early predecessors of ADI. Science Service was an organization founded by the newspaper publisher E.W. Scripps and originally aimed at the betterment of society through the popularization of science. When Watson Davis became director of Science Service in 1933, he shifted its focus toward international scientific cooperation, publication, and bibliography. Davis established Bibliofilm Service in 1934 as an arm of Science Service that would specialize in the use of microfilm to fulfill interlibrary loan requests. Another facet of Science Service was its Auxiliary Publication Service, begun in 1936, which also sought to harness the potential of the emerging microphotography technologies. A small number of other documents pertaining to Science Service, Bibliofilm Service, and Auxiliary Publication Service can be found throughout the collection, particularly in the Related Organizations and Subjects series, but the bulk is in this series.
  The Irene Farkas-Conn Research and Historical Files are divided into seven subseries: People, Committees and Administration, Related Groups, Topics, Chronological, Book Sections, and Research Files. The People subseries contains materials (both original and photocopied) by and about ASIS leaders, plus Farkas-Conn's notes. Committees and Administration refers to ADI/ASIS work and achievements. Related Groups comprises materials by and about groups affiliated with ASIS or performing similar missions, such as the International Federation for Documentation (FID). The Topics subseries and the Chronological subseries both focus on the 1930s and 1940s, with special attention paid to ADI's wartime activities. The Book Sections subseries is divided according to Farkas-Conn's planned structure for her book. In each numbered section can be found source materials, notes, and partial drafts. Also included are some of Farkas-Conn's dissertation materials and background resources. The rest of the series is comprised of the Research Files, which contain material that is more generally or loosely organized. It consists mainly of Farkas-Conn's notes, photocopies, and a small number of original documents (correspondence, reports, pamphlets, etc.).
  Materials in this series span the 1930s through the 1970s. Most of Farkas-Conn's notes are undated, but appear to date from the 1970s and 1980s. In all of the subseries, an attempt was made whenever possible to retain Farkas-Conn's original folder headings. However, sometimes it was necessary to make slight changes; for example, combining multiple headings, glossing abbreviations, guessing at illegible text, and supplying missing headings.
  - People
    - Adams, Scott: "Adams Bibliography," 1981 (Box 1)
    - Davis, Watson, 1935-1963 (Box 1)
    - Mooers, C.N.
      - 1950-1961 (Box 1)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Power, E.B. [Power, Eugene], 1935-1975 (Box 1)
      (includes Farkas-Conn's undated notes)
    - Rhyne, White (ASIS legal counsel), 1939-1975 (Box 1)
      (re tax-exempt status)
    - People List, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Committees and Administration
    (within ADI/ASIS)
    - ADI HQ, first decade, Admin/Director [?], 1937 (Box 1)
    - "ASIS date/copies," 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meetings, 1959-1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Chapters, SIGs (Box 1)
    - Committees [various], ca. 1963-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Committees, third decade/HQ issues and others, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (includes much to and from James E. Bryan)
    - HQ [Headquarters], third decade (Box 1)
    - International Relations, 1930s (Box 1)
    - Meetings Proceedings, first decade (Box 1)
    - Notes on ASIS internal history, 1976 and undated (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Related Groups
    - ACLS (American Council of Learned Societies)
      - Foreign copying, 1940 (Box 1)
      - Funding, 1935-1937 (Box 1)
    - ACS (American Chemical Society)
      - 1930s (Box 1)
      - "ACS, 30ies, Other [___?] finances," 1930s (Box 1)
        (illegible)
    - ADI-SLA, 1965 (Box 1)
      (re proposed American Documentation Institute and Special Libraries Association merger)
    - ALA (American Library Association)
      - Librarianship, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
      - Postwar International UWS [?], 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - ARIST ( Annual Review of Information Science and Technology)
      - Proposals, 1964 (Box 1)
      - Volume I/notes, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Auxiliary Publication Service (and ASIS History), 1936-1984 (Box 1)
    - Bibliofilm Service, ADI, 1937-1943 (Box 1)
    - Bibliofilm Service-Army Medical Library correspondence, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Corporation, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Chemical Foundation/Watson Davis, 1935-1965 (Box 1)
    - China project, notes A-Z, 1936 (Box 1)
      (with note "II?")
    - Conventions, public relations, publications, other topics (Box 1)
    - COSATI (Committee on Scientific and Technical Information), Recommendations for National Document Handling Systems in Science and Technology, 3rd, decade, 1965 (Box 1)
    - FID (International Federation for Documentation)
      - "FID International"/"FID WWII," 1937-1979 (Box 1)
      - FID and other groups, 1948-1989 and undated (Box 1)
      - Oxford and London, 1938-1952 (Box 1)
      - 1936-1939 (Box 1)
        (with note on folder, "Council minutes article--important for ADI postwar changes")
      - 1957-1967 (Box 1)
        (mainly ADI business, but with note "Also FID")
      - Third decade, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
        (includes original correspondence from ADI president H.P. Luhn re conflicts between FID and ADI)
    - IIB (Institut International de Bibliographie) (Box 1)
    - ICSI (International Conference on Scientific Information)/Madeleine Henderson, 1958 (Box 1)
    - NAS Archives: National Academy of Sciences-National Research Council, International Relations, International Congresses: Royal Society Scientific Information Conference of 1948 1948-1960 (Box 1)
    - NSF (National Science Foundation), Science Information Task Force, 1977, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Royal Society Empire Scientific Conference, 1946 1948 (Box 2)
    - "Scientific Advisory Board, Govt. & Science," 1935 (Box 2)
    - Science Service
      - "Science Service (Background)," 1926-1937 and undated (Box 2)
      - " Science Service docs" (Box 2)
    - UNESCO (United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization), Committee of Experts on the Photographic Reproduction of Protected Works, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Various U.S. groups: ADI, ALA, NARA (Box 2)
    - Various international groups (Box 2)
  - Topics, scattered dates, mainly 1930s-1970s and undated
    - Abstracting, National Research Council conference, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
    - Adams paper: International scene, Govt. (Box 2)
      (and other articles on sciences and the government)
    - "ADI pol" [policy? politics?] (Box 2)
    - "ADI doctoral dissertation project" (Box 2)
    - "ADI/Funding/Copyright" (Box 2)
    - "ADI general description," 1945 (Box 2)
    - "ADI reprints" (Box 2)
    - "ADI third decade, Education, other [?]" (Box 2)
    - Background on founding of ADI (Box 2)
    - Bibliographies: Collections (Box 2)
    - Bibliography: Indexing (Box 2)
    - "Bibliography proj." [project?] (Box 2)
    - Bibliography/Subject Headings (Box 2)
    - Biographies/Institutional Histories (Box 2)
    - Classification: general/cataloging (Box 2)
    - Computers, History, Des___ [description?] (Box 2)
    - Copyright
      - "Copyright orig." [original?], 1930s (Box 2)
      - "Copyright--SA [?]--Beginnings" (Box 2)
      - "Copyright 3rd decade" (Box 2)
      - "Mostly copyright Binkley" (Box 2)
        (Binkley refers to Robert C. Binkley, chairman of the Joint Committee on Materials for Research)
    - "Current Titles," 1939-1941 (Box 2)
    - "Docum. mtgs." [Documentalists' meetings?] (Box 2)
    - Documentalists [?] (Box 2)
    - "Documentation (Ditmas)" (Box 2)